<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<book id="happy">
  <bookinfo>
    <date>2001-4-27</date>
    <title>Happy User Guide</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Simon</firstname>
      <surname>Marlow</surname>
    </author>
    <author>
      <firstname>Andy</firstname>
      <surname>Gill</surname>
    </author>
    <address><email>simonmar@microsoft.com</email></address>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997-2001</year>
      <holder>Simon Marlow</holder>
    </copyright>
    <abstract>
      <para>This document describes Happy, the Haskell Parser
	Generator, version 1.14.</para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <!-- Table of contents -->
  <toc></toc>
  
<!-- Introduction ========================================================= -->

  <chapter id="happy-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>


    <para> <application>Happy</application> is a parser generator
    system for Haskell, similar to the tool
    <application>yacc</application> for C.  Like
    <application>yacc</application>, it takes a file containing an
    annotated BNF specification of a grammar and produces a Haskell
    module containing a parser for the grammar. </para>
    
    <indexterm><primary>yacc</primary></indexterm>

    <para> <application>Happy</application> is flexible; unlike
    <application>yacc</application>, you can have several
    <application>Happy</application> parsers in the same program, and
    each parser may have multiple entry points.
    <application>Happy</application> can work in conjunction with a
    lexical analyser supplied by the user (either hand-written or
    generated by another program), or it can parse a stream of
    characters directly (but this isn't practical in most cases).  In
    a future version we hope to include a lexical analyser generator
    with <application>Happy</application> as a single package. </para>

    <para> Parsers generated by <application>Happy</application> are
    fast; generally faster than an equivalent parser written using
    parsing combinators or similar tools.  Furthermore, any future
    improvements made to <application>Happy</application> will benefit
    an existing grammar, without need for a rewrite. </para>

    <para> <application>Happy</application> is sufficiently powerful
    to parse Haskell itself - there's a freely available Haskell
    parser written using <application>Happy</application> which can be
    obtained from <ulink
    url="http://www.pms.informatik.uni-muenchen.de/mitarbeiter/panne/haskell_libs/hsparser.html">
    The <literal>hsparser</literal> Page</ulink>, and included with versions of
    GHC from 5.00 onwards.</para>

    <indexterm><primary><literal>hsparser</literal></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Haskell parser</primary>
      <see><literal>hsparser</literal></see>
    </indexterm>

    <para> <application>Happy</application> can currently generate
    four types of parser from a given grammar, the intention being
    that we can experiment with different kinds of functional code to
    see which is the best, and compiler writers can use the different
    types of parser to tune their compilers.  The types of parser
    supported are: </para>
    
    <orderedlist>
      
      <listitem id="item-default-backend">
	<para>`standard' Haskell 98 (should work with any compiler
	that compiles Haskell 98).</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<indexterm scope="all"><primary>arrays</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm scope="all"><primary>back-ends</primary><secondary>arrays</secondary></indexterm>
	<para>standard Haskell using arrays (this is not the default
	because we have found this generates slower parsers than <xref
	linkend="item-default-backend"/>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<indexterm><primary>GHC</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>back-ends</primary><secondary>GHC</secondary></indexterm>
	<para>Haskell with GHC (Glasgow Haskell) extensions. This is a
	slightly faster option than <xref
	linkend="item-default-backend"/> for Glasgow Haskell
	users.</para>
      </listitem>


      <listitem>
	<para>GHC Haskell with string-encoded arrays.  This is the
	fastest/smallest option for GHC users.  If you're using GHC,
	the optimum flag settings are <literal>-agc</literal> (see
	<xref linkend="sec-invoking"/>).</para>
      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>

    <para>Happy can also generate parsers which will dump debugging
    information at run time, showing state transitions and the input
    tokens to the parser.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-compatibility">
      <title>Compatibility</title>

      <para> <application>Happy</application> is written in Glasgow Haskell.  This
      means that (for the time being), you need GHC to compile it.
      Any version of GHC >= 3.02 should work.</para>

      <para> Remember: parsers produced using
      <application>Happy</application> should compile without
      difficulty under any Haskell 98 complier or interpreter.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-reporting-bugs">
      <title>Reporting Bugs</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>bugs, reporting</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para> Any bugs found in <application>Happy</application> should
      be reported to me: Simon Marlow
      <email>simonmar@microsoft.com</email> including all the relevant
      information: the compiler used to compile
      <application>Happy</application>, the command-line options used,
      your grammar file or preferably a cut-down example showing the
      problem, and a description of what goes wrong.  A patch to fix
      the problem would also be greatly appreciated. </para>

      <para> Requests for new features should also be sent to the
      above address, especially if accompanied by patches :-).</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-license">
      <title>License</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>License</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para> Previous versions of <application>Happy</application>
      were covered by the GNU general public license.  We're now
      distributing <application>Happy</application> with a less
      restrictive BSD-style license.  If this license doesn't work for
      you, please get in touch.</para>
      
      <blockquote>
	<para> Copyright 2000, Simon Marlow and Andy Gill.  All rights
	reserved. </para>

	<para> Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with
	or without modification, are permitted provided that the
	following conditions are met: </para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Redistributions of source code must retain the above
            copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
            following disclaimer.</para>
	  </listitem>
 
	  <listitem>
	    <para> Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the
            above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
            following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
            materials provided with the distribution.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS "AS
        IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
        LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
        FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT
        SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT,
        INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
        DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF
        SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS;
        OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF
        LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
        (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF
        THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY
        OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
      </blockquote>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-obtaining">
      <title>Obtaining <application>Happy</application></title>

      <para> <application>Happy</application>'s web page can be found at <ulink
      url="http://www.haskell.org/happy/">http://www.haskell.org/happy/</ulink>.
      <application>Happy</application> source and binaries can be downloaded from
      there.  There are several mirrors of this site, but since they
      tend to move around a bit I won't mention them here. </para>
      
    </sect1>

  </chapter>

<!-- Using Happy =========================================================== -->

  <chapter id="sec-using">
    <title>Using <application>Happy</application></title>

  <para> Users of <application>Yacc</application> will find
  <application>Happy</application> quite familiar.  The basic idea is
  as follows: </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Define the grammar you want to parse in a
      <application>Happy</application> grammar file. </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para> Run the grammar through <application>Happy</application>, to generate
      a compilable Haskell module.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para> Use this module as part of your Haskell program, usually
      in conjunction with a lexical analyser (a function that splits
      the input into ``tokens'', the basic unit of parsing).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para> Let's run through an example.  We'll implement a parser for a
  simple expression syntax, consisting of integers, variables, the
  operators <literal>+</literal>, <literal>-</literal>, <literal>*</literal>,
  <literal>/</literal>, and the form <literal>let var = exp in exp</literal>.
  The grammar file starts off like this:</para>

    <programlisting>
{
module Main where
}
</programlisting>

    <para>At the top of the file is an optional <firstterm>module
    header</firstterm>,
      <indexterm>
	<primary>module</primary>
	<secondary>header</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    which is just a Haskell module header enclosed in braces.  This
    code is emitted verbatim into the generated module, so you can put
    any Haskell code here at all.  In a grammar file, Haskell code is
    always contained between curly braces to distinguish it from the
    grammar.</para>

    <para>In this case, the parser will be a standalone program so
    we'll call the module <literal>Main</literal>.</para>

    <para>Next comes a couple of declarations:</para>

<programlisting>
%name calc
%tokentype { Token }
</programlisting>

    <indexterm>
      <primary><literal>%name</literal></primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary><literal>%tokentype</literal></primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The first line declares the name of the parsing function
    that <application>Happy</application> will generate, in this case
    <literal>calc</literal>.  In many cases, this is the only symbol you need
    to export from the module.</para>

    <para>The second line declares the type of tokens that the parser
    will accept.  The parser (i.e. the function
    <function>calc</function>) will be of type <literal>[Token] ->
    T</literal>, where <literal>T</literal> is the return type of the
    parser, determined by the production rules below.</para>

    <para>Now we declare all the possible tokens:</para>

<programlisting>
%token 
      let             { TokenLet }
      in              { TokenIn }
      int             { TokenInt $$ }
      var             { TokenVar $$ }
      '='             { TokenEq }
      '+'             { TokenPlus }
      '-'             { TokenMinus }
      '*'             { TokenTimes }
      '/'             { TokenDiv }
      '('             { TokenOB }
      ')'             { TokenCB }
</programlisting>

    <indexterm>
      <primary><literal>%token</literal></primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The symbols on the left are the tokens as they will be
    referred to in the rest of the grammar, and to the right of each
    token enclosed in braces is a Haskell pattern that matches the
    token.  The parser will expect to receive a stream of tokens, each
    of which will match one of the given patterns (the definition of
    the <literal>Token</literal> datatype is given later).</para>

    <para>The <literal>&dollar;&dollar;</literal> symbol is a placeholder that
    represents the <emphasis>value</emphasis> of this token.  Normally the value
    of a token is the token itself, but by using the
    <literal>&dollar;&dollar;</literal> symbol you can specify some component
    of the token object to be the value. </para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary><literal>&dollar;&dollar;</literal></primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Like yacc, we include <literal>%%</literal> here, for no real
    reason.</para>

<programlisting>
%%
</programlisting>

    <para>Now we have the production rules for the grammar.</para>

<programlisting>
Exp   : let var '=' Exp in Exp  { Let $2 $4 $6 }
      | Exp1                    { Exp1 $1 }

Exp1  : Exp1 '+' Term           { Plus $1 $3 }
      | Exp1 '-' Term           { Minus $1 $3 }
      | Term                    { Term $1 }

Term  : Term '*' Factor         { Times $1 $3 }
      | Term '/' Factor         { Div $1 $3 }
      | Factor                  { Factor $1 }

Factor			  
      : int                     { Int $1 }
      | var                     { Var $1 }
      | '(' Exp ')'             { Brack $2 }
</programlisting>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>non-terminal</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Each production consists of a <firstterm>non-terminal</firstterm>
    symbol on the left, followed by a colon, followed by one or more
    expansions on the right, separated by <literal>|</literal>.  Each expansion
    has some Haskell code associated with it, enclosed in braces as
    usual.</para>

    <para>The way to think about a parser is with each symbol having a
    `value': we defined the values of the tokens above, and the
    grammar defines the values of non-terminal symbols in terms of
    sequences of other symbols (either tokens or non-terminals).  In a
    production like this:</para>

<programlisting>
n   : t_1 ... t_n   { E }
</programlisting>

    <para>whenever the parser finds the symbols <literal>t_1..t_n</literal> in
    the token stream, it constructs the symbol <literal>n</literal> and gives
    it the value <literal>E</literal>, which may refer to the values of
    <literal>t_1...t_n</literal> using the symbols
    <literal>&dollar;1...&dollar;n</literal>.</para>

    <para>The parser reduces the input using the rules in the grammar
    until just one symbol remains: the first symbol defined in the
    grammar (namely <literal>Exp</literal> in our example).  The value of this
    symbol is the return value from the parser.</para>

    <para>To complete the program, we need some extra code.  The
    grammar file may optionally contain a final code section, enclosed
    in curly braces.</para>

<programlisting>{</programlisting>

    <indexterm>
      <primary><function>happyError</function></primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>All parsers must declare the function <function>happyError</function>,
    which is called when an error is detected. </para>

<programlisting>
happyError :: [Token] -> a
happyError _ = error "Parse error"
</programlisting>

    <para>Note that <literal>happyError</literal> must be polymorphic
    in its return type <literal>a</literal>, which usually means it
    must be a call to <literal>error</literal>.  We'll see in <xref
    linkend="sec-monads"/> how to wrap the parser in a monad so that we
    can do something more sensible with errors.  It's also possible to
    keep track of line numbers in the parser for use in error
    messages, this is described in <xref
    linkend="sec-line-numbers"/>.</para>

    <para>Next we can declare the data type that represents the parsed
    expression:</para>

<programlisting>
data Exp  
      = Let String Exp Exp
      | Exp1 Exp1

data Exp1 
      = Plus Exp1 Term 
      | Minus Exp1 Term 
      | Term Term

data Term 
      = Times Term Factor 
      | Div Term Factor 
      | Factor Factor

data Factor 
      = Int Int 
      | Var String 
      | Brack Exp
</programlisting>

    <para>And the data structure for the tokens...</para>

<programlisting>
data Token
      = TokenLet
      | TokenIn
      | TokenInt Int
      | TokenVar String
      | TokenEq
      | TokenPlus
      | TokenMinus
      | TokenTimes
      | TokenDiv
      | TokenOB
      | TokenCB
 deriving Show
</programlisting>

    <para>... and a simple lexer that returns this data
    structure.</para>

<programlisting>
lexer :: String -> [Token]
lexer [] = []
lexer (c:cs) 
      | isSpace c = lexer cs
      | isAlpha c = lexVar (c:cs)
      | isDigit c = lexNum (c:cs)
lexer ('=':cs) = TokenEq : lexer cs
lexer ('+':cs) = TokenPlus : lexer cs
lexer ('-':cs) = TokenMinus : lexer cs
lexer ('*':cs) = TokenTimes : lexer cs
lexer ('/':cs) = TokenDiv : lexer cs
lexer ('(':cs) = TokenOB : lexer cs
lexer (')':cs) = TokenCB : lexer cs

lexNum cs = TokenInt (read num) : lexer rest
      where (num,rest) = span isDigit cs

lexVar cs =
   case span isAlpha cs of
      ("let",rest) -> TokenLet : lexer rest
      ("in",rest)  -> TokenIn : lexer rest
      (var,rest)   -> TokenVar var : lexer rest
</programlisting>

    <para>And finally a top-level function to take some input, parse
    it, and print out the result.</para>

<programlisting>
main = getContents >>= print . calc . lexer
}
</programlisting>

    <para>And that's it! A whole lexer, parser and grammar in a few
    dozen lines.  Another good example is <application>Happy</application>'s own
    parser. Several features in <application>Happy</application> were developed
    using this as an example.</para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>info file</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>To generate the Haskell module for this parser, type the
    command <command>happy example.y</command> (where
    <filename>example.y</filename> is the name of the grammar file).
    The Haskell module will be placed in a file named
    <filename>example.hs</filename>.  Additionally, invoking the
    command <command>happy example.y -i</command> will produce the
    file <filename>example.info</filename> which contains detailed information
    about the parser, including states and reduction rules (see <xref
    linkend="sec-info-files"/>).  This can be invaluable for debugging
    parsers, but requires some knowledge of the operation of a
    shift-reduce parser. </para>

    <sect1 id="sec-other-datatypes">
      <title>Returning other datatypes</title>

      <para>In the above example, we used a data type to represent the
      syntax being parsed.  However, there's no reason why it has to
      be this way: you could calculate the value of the expression on
      the fly, using productions like this:</para>

<programlisting>
Term  : Term '*' Factor         { $1 * $3 }
      | Term '/' Factor         { $1 / $3 }
      | Factor                  { $1 }
</programlisting>

      <para>The value of a <literal>Term</literal> would be the value of the
      expression itself, and the parser could return an integer.  </para>

      <para>This works for simple expression types, but our grammar
      includes variables and the <literal>let</literal> syntax.  How do we know
      the value of a variable while we're parsing it?  We don't, but
      since the Haskell code for a production can be anything at all,
      we could make it a function that takes an environment of
      variable values, and returns the computed value of the
      expression:</para>

<programlisting>
Exp   : let var '=' Exp in Exp  { \p -> $6 (($2,$4 p):p) }
      | Exp1                    { $1 }

Exp1  : Exp1 '+' Term           { \p -> $1 p + $3 p }
      | Exp1 '-' Term           { \p -> $1 p - $3 p }
      | Term                    { $1 }

Term  : Term '*' Factor         { \p -> $1 p * $3 p }
      | Term '/' Factor         { \p -> $1 p `div` $3 p }
      | Factor                  { $1 }

Factor			  
      : int                     { \p -> $1 }
      | var                     { \p -> case lookup $1 p of
	                                    Nothing -> error "no var"
					    Just i  -> i }
      | '(' Exp ')'             { $2 }
</programlisting>

      <para>The value of each production is a function from an
      environment <emphasis>p</emphasis> to a value.  When parsing a
      <literal>let</literal> construct, we extend the environment with the new
      binding to find the value of the body, and the rule for
      <literal>var</literal> looks up its value in the environment.  There's
      something you can't do in <literal>yacc</literal> :-)</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-sequences"> 
      <title>Parsing sequences</title>

      <para>A common feature in grammars is a <emphasis>sequence</emphasis> of a
      particular syntactic element.  In EBNF, we'd write something
      like <literal>n+</literal> to represent a sequence of one or more
      <literal>n</literal>s, and <literal>n*</literal> for zero or more.
      <application>Happy</application> doesn't support this syntax explicitly, but
      you can define the equivalent sequences using simple
      productions.</para>

      <para>For example, the grammar for <application>Happy</application> itself
      contains a rule like this:</para>

<programlisting>
prods : prod                   { [$1] }
      | prods prod             { $2 : $1 }
</programlisting>

      <para>In other words, a sequence of productions is either a
      single production, or a sequence of productions followed by a
      single production.  This recursive rule defines a sequence of
      one or more productions.</para>

      <para>One thing to note about this rule is that we used
      <emphasis>left recursion</emphasis> to define it - we could have written
      it like this:</para>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>recursion, left vs. right</primary>
      </indexterm>

<programlisting>
prods : prod                  { [$1] }
      | prod prods            { $1 : $2 }
</programlisting>

      <para>The only reason we used left recursion is that
      <application>Happy</application> is more efficient at parsing left-recursive
      rules; they result in a constant stack-space parser, whereas
      right-recursive rules require stack space proportional to the
      length of the list being parsed.  This can be extremely
      important where long sequences are involved, for instance in
      automatically generated output.  For example, the parser in GHC
      used to use right-recursion to parse lists, and as a result it
      failed to parse some <application>Happy</application>-generated modules due
      to running out of stack space!</para>

      <para>One implication of using left recursion is that the resulting
      list comes out reversed, and you have to reverse it again to get
      it in the original order.  Take a look at the
      <application>Happy</application> grammar for Haskell for many examples of
      this.</para>

      <para>Parsing sequences of zero or more elements requires a
      trivial change to the above pattern:</para>

<programlisting>
prods : {- empty -}           { [] }
      | prods prod            { $2 : $1 }
</programlisting>

      <para>Yes - empty productions are allowed.  The normal
      convention is to include the comment <literal>{- empty -}</literal> to
      make it more obvious to a reader of the code what's going
      on.</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-separators">
	<title>Sequences with separators</title>

	<para>A common type of sequence is one with a
        <emphasis>separator</emphasis>: for instance function bodies in C
        consist of statements separated by semicolons.  To parse this
        kind of sequence we use a production like this:</para>

<programlisting>
stmts : stmt                   { [$1] }
      | stmts ';' stmt         { $3 : $1 }
</programlisting>

	<para>If the <literal>;</literal> is to be a <emphasis>terminator</emphasis>
        rather than a separator (i.e. there should be one following
        each statement), we can remove the semicolon from the above
        rule and redefine <literal>stmt</literal> as</para>

<programlisting>
stmt : stmt1 ';'              { $1 }
</programlisting>

	<para>where <literal>stmt1</literal> is the real definition of statements.</para>

        <para>We might like to allow extra semicolons between
        statements, to be a bit more liberal in what we allow as legal
        syntax.  We probably just want the parser to ignore these
        extra semicolons, and not generate a ``null statement'' value
        or something.  The following rule parses a sequence or zero or
        more statements separated by semicolons, in which the
        statements may be empty:</para>

<programlisting>
stmts : stmts ';' stmt          { $3 : $1 }
      | stmts ';'               { $1 }
      | stmt			{ [$1] }
      | {- empty -}		{ [] }
</programlisting>

	<para>Parsing sequences of <emphasis>one</emphasis> or more possibly
	null statements is left as an exercise for the reader...</para>

    </sect2>
    </sect1>
    
<!--
    <sect1 id="sec-ambiguities">
      <title>Ambiguities</title>

      <para>(section under construction)</para>

    </sect1>
-->
    
    <sect1 id="sec-Precedences">
      <title>Using Precedences</title>
      <indexterm><primary>precedences</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>associativity</primary></indexterm>

      <para>Going back to our earlier expression-parsing example,
      wouldn't it be nicer if we didn't have to explicitly separate
      the expressions into terms and factors, merely to make it
      clear that <literal>'*'</literal> and <literal>'/'</literal>
      operators bind more tightly than <literal>'+'</literal> and
      <literal>'-'</literal>?</para>

      <para>We could just change the grammar as follows (making the
      appropriate changes to the expression datatype too):</para>

<programlisting>
Exp   : let var '=' Exp in Exp  { Let $2 $4 $6 }
      | Exp '+' Exp             { Plus $1 $3 }
      | Exp '-' Exp             { Minus $1 $3 }
      | Exp '*' Exp             { Times $1 $3 }
      | Exp '/' Exp             { Div $1 $3 }
      | '(' Exp ')'             { Brack $2 }
      | int                     { Int $1 }
      | var                     { Var $1 }
</programlisting>

      <para>but now Happy will complain that there are shift/reduce
      conflicts because the grammar is ambiguous - we haven't
      specified whether e.g. <literal>1 + 2 * 3</literal> is to be
      parsed as <literal>1 + (2 * 3)</literal> or <literal>(1 + 2) *
      3</literal>.  Happy allows these ambiguities to be resolved by
      specifying the <firstterm>precedences</firstterm> of the
      operators involved using directives in the
      header<footnote><para>Users of <literal>yacc</literal> will find
      this familiar, Happy's precedence scheme works in exactly the
      same way.</para></footnote>:</para>

<programlisting>
...
%right in
%left '+' '-'
%left '*' '/'
%%
...
</programlisting>
<indexterm><primary><literal>%left</literal> directive</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary><literal>%right</literal> directive</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary><literal>%nonassoc</literal> directive</primary></indexterm>
      
      <para>The <literal>%left</literal> or <literal>%right</literal>
      directive is followed by a list of terminals, and declares all
      these tokens to be left or right-associative respectively.  The
      precedence of these tokens with respect to other tokens is
      established by the order of the <literal>%left</literal> and
      <literal>%right</literal> directives: earlier means lower
      precedence.  A higher precedence causes an operator to bind more
      tightly; in our example above, because <literal>'*'</literal>
      has a higher precedence than <literal>'+'</literal>, the
      expression <literal>1 + 2 * 3</literal> will parse as <literal>1
      + (2 * 3)</literal>.</para>

      <para>What happens when two operators have the same precedence?
      This is when the <firstterm>associativity</firstterm> comes into
      play.  Operators specified as left associative will cause
      expressions like <literal>1 + 2 - 3</literal> to parse as
      <literal>(1 + 2) - 3</literal>, whereas right-associative
      operators would parse as <literal>1 + (2 - 3)</literal>.  There
      is also a <literal>%nonassoc</literal> directive which indicates
      that the specified operators may not be used together.  For
      example, if we add the comparison operators
      <literal>'>'</literal> and <literal>'&lt;'</literal> to our
      grammar, then we would probably give their precedence as:</para>

<programlisting>...
%right in
%nonassoc '>' '&lt;'
%left '+' '-'
%left '*' '/'
%%
...</programlisting>

      <para>which indicates that <literal>'>'</literal> and
      <literal>'&lt;'</literal> bind less tightly than the other
      operators, and the non-associativity causes expressions such as
      <literal>1 > 2 > 3</literal> to be disallowed.</para>

      <sect2 id="how-precedence-works">
	<title>How precedence works</title>

	<para>The precedence directives, <literal>%left</literal>,
	<literal>%right</literal> and <literal>%nonassoc</literal>,
	assign precedence levels to the tokens in the declaration.  A
	rule in the grammar may also have a precedence: if the last
	terminal in the left hand side of the rule has a precedence,
	then this is the precedence of the whole rule.</para>

	<para>The precedences are used to resolve ambiguities in the
	grammar.  If there is a shift/reduce conflict, then the
	precedence of the rule and the lookahead token are examined in
	order to resolve the conflict:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>If the precedence of the rule is higher, then the
	    conflict is resolved as a reduce.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>If the precedence of the lookahead token is higher,
	    then the conflict is resolved as a shift.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>If the precedences are equal, then</para>
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>If the token is left-associative, then reduce</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>If the token is right-associative, then shift</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>If the token is non-associative, then fail</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>If either the rule or the token has no precedence,
	    then the default is to shift (these conflicts are reported
	    by Happy, whereas ones that are automatically resolved by
	    the precedence rules are not).</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="context-precedence">
	<title>Context-dependent Precedence</title>
	
	<para>The precedence of an individual rule can be overriden,
	using <firstterm>context precedence</firstterm>.  This is
	useful when, for example, a particular token has a different
	precedence depending on the context.  A common example is the
	minus sign: it has high precedence when used as prefix
	negation, but a lower precedence when used as binary
	subtraction.</para>

	<para>We can implement this in Happy as follows:</para>

<programlisting>%right in
%nonassoc '>' '&lt;'
%left '+' '-'
%left '*' '/'
%left NEG
%%

Exp   : let var '=' Exp in Exp  { Let $2 $4 $6 }
      | Exp '+' Exp             { Plus $1 $3 }
      | Exp '-' Exp             { Minus $1 $3 }
      | Exp '*' Exp             { Times $1 $3 }
      | Exp '/' Exp             { Div $1 $3 }
      | '(' Exp ')'             { Brack $2 }
      | '-' Exp %prec NEG       { Negate $2 }
      | int                     { Int $1 }
      | var                     { Var $1 }</programlisting>
<indexterm><primary><literal>%prec</literal> directive</primary></indexterm>

	<para>We invent a new token <literal>NEG</literal> as a
	placeholder for the precedence of our prefix negation rule.
	The <literal>NEG</literal> token doesn't need to appear in
	a <literal>%token</literal> directive.  The prefix negation
	rule has a <literal>%prec NEG</literal> directive attached,
	which overrides the default precedence for the rule (which
	would normally be the precedence of '-') with the precedence
	of <literal>NEG</literal>.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-type-signatures">
      <title>Type Signatures</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>type</primary>
	<secondary>signatures in grammar</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><application>Happy</application> allows you to include type signatures
      in the grammar file itself, to indicate the type of each
      production.  This has several benefits:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para> Documentation: including types in the grammar helps
          to document the grammar for someone else (and indeed
          yourself) reading the code.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Fixing type errors in the generated module can become
          slightly easier if <application>Happy</application> has inserted type
          signatures for you.  This is a slightly dubious benefit,
          since type errors in the generated module are still somewhat
          difficult to find.  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Type signatures generally help the Haskell compiler
          to compile the parser faster.  This is important when really
          large grammar files are being used.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The syntax for type signatures in the grammar file is as
      follows:</para>

<programlisting>
stmts   :: { [ Stmt ] }
stmts   : stmts stmt                { $2 : $1 }
	| stmt                      { [$1] }
</programlisting>

      <para>In fact, you can leave out the superfluous occurrence of
      <literal>stmts</literal>:</para>

<programlisting>
stmts   :: { [ Stmt ] }
	: stmts stmt                { $2 : $1 }
	| stmt                      { [$1] }
</programlisting>

      <para>Note that currently, you have to include type signatures
      for <emphasis>all</emphasis> the productions in the grammar to benefit
      from the second and third points above.  This is due to boring
      technical reasons, but it is hoped that this restriction can be
      removed in the future.</para>

    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="sec-monads">
      <title>Monadic Parsers</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>monadic</primary>
	<secondary>parsers</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><application>Happy</application> has support for threading a monad
      through the generated parser.  This might be useful for several
      reasons:</para>

      <itemizedlist>

	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>parse errors</primary>
	    <secondary>handling</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
<!--	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>error</primary>
	    <secondary>parse</secondary>
	    <see>parse errors</see>
	  </indexterm> 
-->
	  <para> Handling parse errors by using an exception monad
          (see <xref linkend="sec-exception"/>).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>line numbers</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para> Keeping track of line numbers in the input file, for
          example for use in error messages (see <xref
          linkend="sec-line-numbers"/>).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Performing IO operations during parsing.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Parsing languages with context-dependencies (such as
          C) require some state in the parser.</para>
	</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

      <para>Adding monadic support to your parser couldn't be simpler.
      Just add the following directive to the declaration section of
      the grammar file:</para>

<programlisting>
%monad { &lt;type&gt; } [ { &lt;then&gt; } { &lt;return&gt; } ]
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
	<primary><literal>%monad</literal></primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>where <literal>&lt;type&gt;</literal> is the type constructor for
      the monad, <literal>&lt;then&gt;</literal> is the bind operation of the
      monad, and <literal>&lt;return&gt;</literal> is the return operation. If
      you leave out the names for the bind and return operations,
      <application>Happy</application> assumes that <literal>&lt;type&gt;</literal> is an
      instance of the standard Haskell type class <literal>Monad</literal> and
      uses the overloaded names for the bind and return
      operations.</para>

      <para>When this declaration is included in the grammar,
      <application>Happy</application> makes a couple of changes to the generated
      parser: the types of the main parser function and
      <literal>happyError</literal> become <literal>[Token] -&gt; P a</literal> where
      <literal>P</literal> is the monad type constructor, and the function must
      be polymorphic in <literal>a</literal>.  In other words,
      <application>Happy</application> adds an application of the
      <literal>&lt;return&gt;</literal> operation defined in the declaration
      above, around the result of the parser (<literal>happyError</literal> is
      affected because it must have the same return type as the
      parser).  And that's all it does.</para>

      <indexterm>
	<primary><function>happyError</function></primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>This still isn't very useful: all you can do is return
      something of monadic type from <literal>happyError</literal>.  How do you
      specify that the productions can also have type <literal>P a</literal>?
      Most of the time, you don't want a production to have this type:
      you'd have to write explicit <literal>returnP</literal>s everywhere.
      However, there may be a few rules in a grammar that need to get
      at the monad, so <application>Happy</application> has a special syntax for
      monadic actions:</para>

<programlisting>
n  :  t_1 ... t_n          {% &lt;expr&gt; }
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>monadic</primary>
	<secondary>actions</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>The <literal>%</literal> in the action indicates that this is a
      monadic action, with type <literal>P a</literal>, where <literal>a</literal> is
      the real return type of the production.  When
      <application>Happy</application> reduces one of these rules, it evaluates the
      expression </para>

<programlisting>
&lt;expr&gt; `then` \result -> &lt;continue parsing&gt;
</programlisting>

      <para><application>Happy</application> uses <literal>result</literal> as the real
      semantic value of the production.  During parsing, several
      monadic actions might be reduced, resulting in a sequence
      like</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;expr1&gt; `then` \r1 ->
&lt;expr2&gt; `then` \r2 ->
...
return &lt;expr3&gt;
</programlisting>

      <para>The monadic actions are performed in the order that they
      are <emphasis>reduced</emphasis>.  If we consider the parse as a tree,
      then reductions happen in a depth-first left-to-right manner.
      The great thing about adding a monad to your parser is that it
      doesn't impose any performance overhead for normal reductions -
      only the monadic ones are translated like this.</para>

      <para>Take a look at the Haskell parser for a good illustration
      of how to use a monad in your parser: it contains examples of
      all the principles discussed in this section, namely parse
      errors, a threaded lexer, line/column numbers, and state
      communication between the parser and lexer.</para>

      <para>The following sections consider a couple of uses for
      monadic parsers, and describe how to also thread the monad
      through the lexical analyser.</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-exception">
	<title>Handling Parse Errors</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>parse errors</primary>
	  <secondary>handling</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	    
      <para>It's not very convenient to just call <literal>error</literal> when
      a parse error is detected: in a robust setting, you'd like the
      program to recover gracefully and report a useful error message
      to the user.  Exceptions (of which errors are a special case)
      are normally implemented in Haskell by using an exception monad,
      something like:</para>

<programlisting>
data E a = Ok a | Failed String

thenE :: E a -> (a -> E b) -> E b
m `thenE` k = 
   case m of 
       Ok a -> k a
	 Failed e -> Failed e

returnE :: a -> E a
returnE a = Ok a

failE :: String -> E a
failE err = Failed err

catchE :: E a -> (String -> E a) -> E a
catchE m k = 
   case m of
      Ok a -> OK a
	Failed e -> k e
</programlisting>

	<para>This monad just uses a string as the error type.  The
        functions <literal>thenE</literal> and <literal>returnE</literal> are the usual
        bind and return operations of the monad, <literal>failE</literal>
        raises an error, and <literal>catchE</literal> is a combinator for
        handling exceptions.</para>

	<para>We can add this monad to the parser with the declaration</para>

<programlisting>
%monad { E } { thenE } { returnE }
</programlisting>

	<para>Now, without changing the grammar, we can change the
        definition of <literal>happyError</literal> and have something sensible
        happen for a parse error:</para>

<programlisting>
happyError tokens = failE "Parse error"
</programlisting>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary><function>happyError</function></primary>
	  </indexterm>

	<para>The parser now raises an exception in the monad instead
	of bombing out on a parse error.</para>

	<para>We can also generate errors during parsing.  There are
        times when it is more convenient to parse a more general
        language than that which is actually intended, and check it
        later.  An example comes from Haskell, where the precedence
        values in infix declarations must be between 0 and 9:</para>

<programlisting>prec :: { Int }
      : int    {% if $1 &lt; 0 || $1 > 9 
	                then failE "Precedence out of range"
		        else returnE $1
		}</programlisting>

	<para>The monadic action allows the check to be placed in the
	parser itself, where it belongs.</para>

    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="sec-lexers">
      <title>Threaded Lexers</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>lexer, threaded</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>monadic</primary>
	  <secondary>lexer</secondary>
	</indexterm>

	<para><application>Happy</application> allows the monad concept to be
	extended to the lexical analyser, too.  This has several
	useful consequences:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> Lexical errors can be treated in the same way as
            parse errors, using an exception monad.</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>parse errors</primary>
	      <secondary>lexical</secondary>
	    </indexterm>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> Information such as the current file and line
            number can be communicated between the lexer and
            parser. </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> General state communication between the parser and
            lexer - for example, implementation of the Haskell layout
            rule requires this kind of interaction.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> IO operations can be performed in the lexer - this
            could be useful for following import/include declarations
            for instance.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>A monadic lexer is requested by adding the following
	declaration to the grammar file:</para>

<programlisting>
%lexer { &lt;lexer&gt; } { &lt;eof&gt; }
</programlisting>
	
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%lexer</literal></primary>
	</indexterm>

	<para>where <literal>&lt;lexer&gt;</literal> is the name of the lexical
        analyser function, and <literal>&lt;eof&gt;</literal> is a token that
        is to be treated as the end of file.</para>

	<para>When using a monadic lexer, the parser no longer reads a
        list of tokens.  Instead, it calls the lexical analysis
        function for each new token to be read.  This has the side
        effect of eliminating the intermediate list of tokens, which
        is a slight performance win.</para>

	<para>The type of the main parser function and
        <literal>happyError</literal> is now just <literal>P a</literal> - the input is
        being handled completely within the monad.</para>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><function>happyError</function></primary>
	</indexterm>

	<para>The lexical analysis function must have the following
	type:</para>

<programlisting>
lexer :: (Token -> P a) -> P a
</programlisting>

	<para>where <literal>P</literal> is the monad type constructor declared
        with <literal>%monad</literal>, and <literal>a</literal> can be replaced by the
        parser return type if desired.</para>

	<para>You can see from this type that the lexer takes a
        <emphasis>continuation</emphasis> as an argument.  The lexer is to find
        the next token, and pass it to this continuation to carry on
        with the parse.  Obviously, we need to keep track of the input
        in the monad somehow, so that the lexer can do something
        different each time it's called!</para>

	<para>Let's take the exception monad above, and extend it to
        add the input string so that we can use it with a threaded
        lexer.</para>

<programlisting>
data ParseResult a = Ok a | Failed String
type P a = String -> ParseResult a

thenP :: P a -> (a -> P b) -> P b
m `thenP` k = \s ->
   case m s of 
       Ok a -> k a s
	 Failed e -> Failed e

returnP :: a -> P a
returnP a = \s -> Ok a

failP :: String -> P a
failP err = \s -> Failed err

catchP :: P a -> (String -> P a) -> P a
catchP m k = \s ->
   case m s of
      Ok a -> OK a
	Failed e -> k e s
</programlisting>

	<para>Notice that this isn't a real state monad - the input
        string just gets passed around, not returned.  Our lexer will
        now look something like this:</para>

<programlisting>
lexer :: (Token -> P a) -> P a
lexer cont s = 
    ... lexical analysis code ...
    cont token s'
</programlisting>

	<para>the lexer grabs the continuation and the input string,
        finds the next token <literal>token</literal>, and passes it together
        with the remaining input string <literal>s'</literal> to the
        continuation.</para>

	<para>We can now indicate lexical errors by ignoring the
        continuation and calling <literal>failP "error message" s</literal>
        within the lexer (don't forget to pass the input string to
        make the types work out).</para>

	<para>This may all seem a bit weird.  Why, you ask, doesn't
        the lexer just have type <literal>P Token</literal>?  Well, the
        decision was taken to use a continuation purely for
        performance reasons.  If the lexer must return a token, then
        it turns out that the input string must be a real state
        object, and the monad has to return it as well as pass it
        around.  If you want a lexer of type <literal>P Token</literal>, then
        just define a wrapper to deal with the continuation:</para>

<programlisting>
lexwrap :: (Token -> P a) -> P a
lexwrap cont = real_lexer `thenP` \token -> cont token
</programlisting>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec-line-numbers">
      <title>Line Numbers</title>

	<indexterm>
	  <primary>line numbers</primary>
	</indexterm>

	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%newline</literal></primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>Previous versions of <application>Happy</application> had a
        <literal>%newline</literal> directive that enabled simple line numbers
        to be counted by the parser and referenced in the actions.  We
        warned you that this facility may go away and be replaced by
        something more general, well guess what? :-)</para>

	<para>Line numbers can now be dealt with quite
        straightforwardly using a monadic parser/lexer combination.
        Ok, we have to extend the monad a bit more:</para>

<programlisting>
type LineNumber = Int
type P a = String -> LineNumber -> ParseResult a

getLineNo :: P LineNumber
getLineNo = \s l -> Ok l
</programlisting>

	<para>(the rest of the functions in the monad follow by just
        adding the extra line number argument in the same way as the
        input string).  Again, the line number is just passed down,
        not returned: this is OK because of the continuation-based
        lexer that can change the line number and pass the new one to
        the continuation.</para>

	<para>The lexer can now update the line number as follows:</para>

<programlisting>
lexer cont s =
  case s of
     '\n':s  ->  \line -> lexer cont s (line + 1)
     ... rest of lexical analysis ...
</programlisting>

	<para>It's as simple as that.  Take a look at
        <application>Happy</application>'s own parser if you have the sources lying
        around, it uses a monad just like the one above.</para>

        <para>Reporting the line number of a parse error is achieved
        by changing <literal>happyError</literal> to look something like
        this:</para>

<programlisting>
happyError :: P a
happyError = getLineNo `thenP` \line -> 
             failP (show line ++ ": parse error")
</programlisting>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><function>happyError</function></primary>
	</indexterm>

	<para>We can also get hold of the line number during parsing,
        to put it in the parsed data structure for future reference.
        A good way to do this is to have a production in the grammar
        that returns the current line number: </para>

<programlisting>lineno :: { LineNumber }
        : {- empty -}      {% getLineNo }</programlisting>

	<para>The semantic value of <literal>lineno</literal> is the line
        number of the last token read - this will always be the token
        directly following the <literal>lineno</literal> symbol in the grammar,
        since <application>Happy</application> always keeps one lookahead token in
        reserve.</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-monad-summary">
	<title>Summary</title>

	<para>The types of various functions related to the parser are
        dependent on what combination of <literal>%monad</literal> and
        <literal>%lexer</literal> directives are present in the grammar.  For
        reference, we list those types here.  In the following types,
        <emphasis>t</emphasis> is the return type of the
        parser.  A type containing a type variable indicates that the
        specified function must be polymorphic.</para>

	<indexterm>
	  <primary>type</primary>
	  <secondary>of <function>happyError</function></secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>type</primary>
	  <secondary>of parser</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>type</primary>
	  <secondary>of lexer</secondary>
	</indexterm>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title> No <literal>&percnt;monad</literal> or
	      <literal>&percnt;lexer</literal> </title>
	      <para>
<programlisting>
parse      :: [Token] -> <emphasis>t</emphasis>
happyError :: [Token] -> a
</programlisting>
</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title> with <literal>%monad</literal> </title>
	      <para>
<programlisting>
parse      :: [Token] -> P <emphasis>t</emphasis>
happyError :: [Token] -> P a
</programlisting>
</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>


	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title> with <literal>%lexer</literal> </title>
	      <para><programlisting>
parse      :: T <emphasis>t</emphasis>
happyError :: T a
lexer      :: (Token -> T a) -> T a
</programlisting>
where the type constructor <literal>T</literal> is whatever you want (usually <literal>T
a = String -> a</literal>.  I'm not sure if this is useful, or even if it works
properly.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title> with <literal>%monad</literal> and <literal>%lexer</literal> </title>
	      <para><programlisting>
parse      :: P <emphasis>t</emphasis>
happyError :: P a
lexer      :: (Token -> P a) -> P a
</programlisting>
</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-error">
      <title>The Error Token</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>error token</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><application>Happy</application> supports a limited form of error
      recovery, using the special symbol <literal>error</literal> in a grammar
      file.  When <application>Happy</application> finds a parse error during
      parsing, it automatically inserts the <literal>error</literal> symbol; if
      your grammar deals with <literal>error</literal> explicitly, then it can
      detect the error and carry on.</para>

      <para>For example, the <application>Happy</application> grammar for Haskell
      uses error recovery to implement Haskell layout.  The grammar
      has a rule that looks like this:</para>

<programlisting>
close : '}'                  { () }
      | error		     { () }
</programlisting>

      <para>This says that a close brace in a layout-indented context
      may be either a curly brace (inserted by the lexical analyser),
      or a parse error.  </para>

      <para>This rule is used to parse expressions like <literal>let x
      = e in e'</literal>: the layout system inserts an open brace before
      <literal>x</literal>, and the occurrence of the <literal>in</literal> symbol
      generates a parse error, which is interpreted as a close brace
      by the above rule.</para>

      <indexterm>
	<primary><application>yacc</application></primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>Note for <literal>yacc</literal> users: this form of error recovery
      is strictly more limited than that provided by <literal>yacc</literal>.
      During a parse error condition, <literal>yacc</literal> attempts to
      discard states and tokens in order to get back into a state
      where parsing may continue; <application>Happy</application> doesn't do this.
      The reason is that normal <literal>yacc</literal> error recovery is
      notoriously hard to describe, and the semantics depend heavily
      on the workings of a shift-reduce parser.  Furthermore,
      different implementations of <literal>yacc</literal> appear to implement
      error recovery differently.  <application>Happy</application>'s limited error
      recovery on the other hand is well-defined, as is just
      sufficient to implement the Haskell layout rule (which is why it
      was added in the first place).</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-multiple-parsers">
      <title>Generating Multiple Parsers From a Single Grammar</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>multiple parsers</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>It is often useful to use a single grammar to describe
      multiple parsers, where each parser has a different top-level
      non-terminal, but parts of the grammar are shared between
      parsers.  A classic example of this is an interpreter, which
      needs to be able to parse both entire files and single
      expressions: the expression grammar is likely to be identical
      for the two parsers, so we would like to use a single grammar
      but have two entry points.</para>

      <para><application>Happy</application> lets you do this by
      allowing multiple <literal>%name</literal> directives in the
      grammar file.  The <literal>%name</literal> directive takes an
      optional second parameter specifying the top-level
      non-terminal for this parser, so we may specify multiple parsers
      like so:</para>
      <indexterm><primary><literal>%name</literal> directive</primary>
      </indexterm>

<programlisting>
%name parse1 non-terminal1
%name parse2 non-terminal2
</programlisting>

      <para><application>Happy</application> will generate from this a
      module which defines two functions <function>parse1</function>
      and <function>parse2</function>, which parse the grammars given
      by <literal>non-terminal1</literal> and
      <literal>non-terminal2</literal> respectively.  Each parsing
      function will of course have a different type, depending on the
      type of the appropriate non-terminal.</para>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-glr">

    <chapterinfo>
      <copyright>
        <year>2004</year>
        <holder>University of Durham, Paul Callaghan, Ben Medlock</holder>
      </copyright>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Generalized LR Parsing</title>

    <para>This chapter explains how to use the GLR parsing extension,
    which allows <application>Happy</application> to parse ambiguous 
    grammars and produce useful results.
    This extension is triggered with the <option>--glr</option> flag, 
    which causes <application>Happy</application>
    to use a different driver for the LALR(1) parsing
    tables. The result of parsing is a structure which encodes compactly
    <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the possible parses. 
    There are two options for how semantic information is combined with
    the structural information. 
    </para>

    <para>
    This extension was developed by Paul Callaghan and Ben Medlock
    (University of Durham). It is based on the structural parser
    implemented in Medlock's undergraduate project, but significantly
    extended and improved by Callaghan. 
    Bug reports, comments, questions etc should be sent to 
    <email>P.C.Callaghan@durham.ac.uk</email>. 
    Further information can be found on Callaghan's
    <ulink url="http://www.dur.ac.uk/p.c.callaghan/happy-glr">GLR parser
    page</ulink>.

	
    </para>

    <sect1 id="sec-glr-intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>
      Here's an ambiguous grammar. It has no information about the 
      associativity of <literal>+</literal>, so for example,
      <literal>1+2+3</literal> can be parsed as 
      <literal>(1+(2+3))</literal> or <literal>((1+2)+3)</literal>. 
      In conventional mode, <application>Happy</application>,
      would complain about a shift/reduce 
      conflict, although it would generate a parser which always shifts 
      in such a conflict, and hence would produce <emphasis>only</emphasis>
      the first alternative above.
      </para>

      <programlisting>
      E -> E + E
      E -> i       -- any integer
      </programlisting>

      <para>
      GLR parsing will accept this grammar without complaint, and produce
      a result which encodes <emphasis>both</emphasis> alternatives
      simultaneously. Now consider the more interesting example of
      <literal>1+2+3+4</literal>, which has five distinct parses -- try to
      list them! You will see that some of the subtrees are identical. 
      A further property of the GLR output is that such sub-results are 
      shared, hence efficiently represented: there is no combinatorial 
      explosion.
      Below is the simplified output of the GLR parser for this example.
      </para>

      <programlisting>
	Root (0,7,G_E)
	(0,1,G_E)     => [[(0,1,Tok '1'))]]
	(0,3,G_E)     => [[(0,1,G_E),(1,2,Tok '+'),(2,3,G_E)]]
	(0,5,G_E)     => [[(0,1,G_E),(1,2,Tok '+'),(2,5,G_E)]
	                 ,[(0,3,G_E),(3,4,Tok '+'),(4,5,G_E)]]
	(0,7,G_E)     => [[(0,3,G_E),(3,4,Tok '+'),(4,7,G_E)]
	                 ,[(0,1,G_E),(1,2,Tok '+'),(2,7,G_E)]
	                 ,[(0,5,G_E),(5,6,Tok '+'),(6,7,G_E)]}]
	(2,3,G_E)     => [[(2,3,Tok '2'))]}]
	(2,5,G_E)     => [[(2,3,G_E),(3,4,Tok '+'),(4,5,G_E)]}]
	(2,7,G_E)     => [[(2,3,G_E),(3,4,Tok '+'),(4,7,G_E)]}
	                 ,[(2,5,G_E),(5,6,Tok '+'),(6,7,G_E)]}]
	(4,5,G_E)     => [[(4,5,Tok '3'))]}]
	(4,7,G_E)     => [[(4,5,G_E),(5,6,Tok '+'),(6,7,G_E)]}]
	(6,7,G_E)     => [[(6,7,Tok '4'))]}]
      </programlisting>

      <para>
      This is a directed, acyclic and-or graph. 
      The node "names" are of form <literal>(a,b,c)</literal>
      where <literal>a</literal> and <literal>b</literal>
      are the start and end points (as positions in the input string)
      and <literal>c</literal> is a category (or name of grammar rule). 
      For example <literal>(2,7,G_E)</literal> spans positions 2 to 7
      and contains analyses which match the <literal>E</literal>
      grammar rule.
      Such analyses are given as a list of alternatives (disjunctions), 
      each corresponding to some use of a production of that 
      category, which in turn are a conjunction of sub-analyses,
      each represented as a node in the graph or an instance of a token.
      </para>

      <para>
      Hence <literal>(2,7,G_E)</literal> contains two alternatives,
      one which has <literal>(2,3,G_E)</literal> as its first child
      and the other with <literal>(2,5,G_E)</literal> as its first child,
      respectively corresponding to sub-analyses 
      <literal>(2+(3+4))</literal> and <literal>((2+3)+4)</literal>.
      Both alternatives have the token <literal>+</literal> as their
      second child, but note that they are difference occurrences of
      <literal>+</literal> in the input! 
      We strongly recommend looking at such results in graphical form 
      to understand these points. If you build the 
      <literal>expr-eval</literal> example in the directory
      <literal>examples/glr</literal> (NB you need to use GHC for this,
      unless you know how to use the <option>-F</option> flag for Hugs),
      running the example will produce a file which can be viewed with
      the <emphasis>daVinci</emphasis> graph visualization tool.
      (See <ulink url="http://www.informatik.uni-bremen.de/~davinci/"/>
       for more information. Educational use licenses are currently 
	available without charge.)  
      </para>

      <para>
      The GLR extension also allows semantic information to be attached 
      to productions, as in conventional <application>Happy</application>, 
      although there are further issues to consider.
      Two modes are provided, one for simple applications and one for more
      complex use.
      See <xref linkend="sec-glr-semantics"/>.
      The extension is also integrated with <application>Happy</application>'s
      token handling, e.g. extraction of information from tokens. 
      </para>

      <para>
      One key feature of this implementation in Haskell is that its main 
      result is a <emphasis>graph</emphasis>.
      Other implementations effectively produce a list of trees, but this
      limits practical use to small examples. 
      For large and interesting applications, some of which are discussed
      in <xref linkend="sec-glr-misc-applications"/>, a graph is essential due
      to the large number of possibilities and the need to analyse the
      structure of the ambiguity. Converting the graph to trees could produce
      huge numbers of results and will lose information about sharing etc.
      </para>

      <para>
      One final comment. You may have learnt through using 
      <application>yacc</application>-style tools that ambiguous grammars 
      are to be avoided, and that ambiguity is something that appears 
      only in Natural Language processing. 
      This is definitely not true. 
      Many interesting grammars are ambiguous, and with GLR tools they 
      can be used effectively. 
      We hope you enjoy exploring this fascinating area!
      </para>

    </sect1>
     
    <sect1 id="sec-glr-using">
      <title>Basic use of a Happy-generated GLR parser</title>

      <para>
      This section explains how to generate and to use a GLR parser to 
      produce structural results.
      Please check the examples for further information.
      Discussion of semantic issues comes later; see
      <xref linkend="sec-glr-semantics"/>.
      </para>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-using-intro">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>
	The process of generating a GLR parser is broadly the same as
	for standard <application>Happy</application>. You write a grammar
	specification, run <application>Happy</application> on this to 
	generate some Haskell code, then compile and link this into your
	program. 
        </para>
        <para>
	Most of the features of <application>Happy</application> still
	work, but note the important points below.
        </para>
	<variablelist>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>module header</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       The GLR parser is generated in TWO files, one for data and 
	       one for the driver. This is because the driver code needs 
	       to be optimized, but for large parsers with lots of data,
	       optimizing the data tables too causes compilation to be 
	       too slow. 
	       </para>
	       <para>
	       Given a file <literal>Foo.y</literal>, file
	       <literal>FooData.hs</literal> is generated with basic type 
	       information, the parser tables, and the header and tail code 
	       that was included in the parser specification. 
	       Note that <application>Happy</application> generates the 
	       module declaration line, so you should NOT give it in the 
	       grammar file. 
	       The driver is placed in file <literal>Foo.hs</literal>, and
	       does not contain any user-supplied text.
	       </para>

	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>export of lexer</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       You can declare a lexer (and error token) with the 
	       <literal>%lexer</literal> directive as normal, but the 
	       generated parser does NOT call this lexer automatically.
	       The action of the directive is only to 
	       <emphasis>export</emphasis> the lexer function to the top 
	       level. This is because some applications need finer control
	       of the lexing process.
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>

	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>precedence information</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       This still works, but note the reasons.
	       The precedence and associativity declarations are used in 
	       <application>Happy</application>'s LR table creation to 
	       resolve certain conflicts. It does this by retaining the 
	       actions implied by the declarations and removing the ones 
	       which clash with these. 
	       The GLR parser back-end then produces code from these 
	       filtered tables, hence the rejected actions are never
	       considered by the GLR parser. 
	       </para>
	       <para>
	       Hence, declaring precedence and associativity is still 
	       a good thing, since it avoids a certain amount of ambiguity
	       that the user knows how to remove. 
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>monad directive</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       There is some support for monadic parsers.
	       The "tree decoding" mode 
	       (see <xref linkend="sec-glr-semantics-tree"/>) can use the
	       information given in the <literal>%monad</literal> 
	       declaration to monadify the decoding process. 
	       This is explained in more detail in
	       <xref linkend="sec-glr-semantics-tree-monad"/>.
	       </para>
	       <para>
	       <emphasis>Note</emphasis>: the generated parsers don't include
	       Ashley Yakeley's monad context information yet. It is currently
	       just ignored. 
	       If this is a problem, email and I'll make the changes required.
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>parser name directive</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       This has no effect at present. It will probably remain this 
	       way: if you want to control names, you could use qualified 
	       import.
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>type information on non-terminals</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       The generation of semantic code relies on type information
	       given in the grammar specification. If you don't give an
	       explicit signature, the type <literal>()</literal> is 
	       assumed. If you get type clashes mentioning 
	       <literal>()</literal> you may need to add type annotations.
	       Similarly, if you don't supply code for the semantic rule 
	       portion, then the value <literal>()</literal> is used.
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term><literal>error</literal> symbol in grammars, and recovery
		</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       No attempt to implement this yet. Any use of 
	       <literal>error</literal> in grammars is thus ignored, and
	       parse errors will eventually mean a parse will fail.
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>the token type</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       The type used for tokens <emphasis>must</emphasis> be in 
	       the <literal>Ord</literal> type class (and hence in 
	       <literal>Eq</literal>), plus it is recommended that they
	       are in the <literal>Show</literal> class too. 
	       The ordering is required for the implementation of 
	       ambiguity packing. 
	       It may be possible to relax this requirement, but it 
	       is probably simpler just to require instances of the type 
	       classes. Please tell us if this is a problem.
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-using-main">
        <title>The main function</title>
        <para>
	The driver file exports a function 
	<literal>doParse :: [[UserDefTok]] -> GLRResult</literal>. 
	If you are using several parsers, use qualified naming to 
	distinguish them.
	<literal>UserDefTok</literal> is a synonym for the type declared with 
	the <literal>%tokentype</literal> directive.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-using-input">
        <title>The input</title>
        <para>
	The input to <literal>doParse</literal> is a list of 
	<emphasis>list of</emphasis> token values. 
	The outer level represents the sequence of input symbols, and 
	the inner list represents ambiguity in the tokenisation of each
	input symbol. 
	For example, the word "run" can be at least a noun or a verb, 
	hence the inner list will contain at least two values.
	If your tokens are not ambiguous, you will need to convert each
	token to a singleton list before parsing. 
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-using-output">
        <title>The Parse Result</title>
        <para>
	The parse result is expressed with the following types. 
	A successful parse yields a forest (explained below) and a single 
	root node for the forest.
	A parse may fail for one of two reasons: running out of input or
	a (global) parse error. A global parse error means that it was 
	not possible to continue parsing <emphasis>any</emphasis> of the
	live alternatives; this is different from a local error, which simply
	means that the current alternative dies and we try some other 
	alternative. In both error cases, the forest at failure point is 
	returned, since it may contain useful information. 
	Unconsumed tokens are returned when there is a global parse error.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
	type ForestId = (Int,Int,GSymbol)
	data GSymbol  = &lt;... automatically generated ...&gt;
	type Forest   = FiniteMap ForestId [Branch]
	type RootNode = ForestId
	type Tokens   = [[(Int, GSymbol)]]
	data Branch   = Branch {b_sem :: GSem, b_nodes :: [ForestId]}
	data GSem     = &lt;... automatically generated ...&gt;

	data GLRResult
	 = ParseOK     RootNode Forest    -- forest with root
	 | ParseError  Tokens   Forest    -- partial forest with bad input
	 | ParseEOF             Forest    -- partial forest (missing input)
        </programlisting>
	<para>
	Conceptually, the parse forest is a directed, acyclic and-or
	graph. It is represented by a mapping of <literal>ForestId</literal>s
	to lists of possible analyses. The <literal>FiniteMap</literal> 
	type is used to provide efficient and convenient access.
	The <literal>ForestId</literal> type identifies nodes in the 
	graph, named by the range of input they span and the category of
	analysis they license. <literal>GSymbol</literal> is generated 
	automatically as a union of the names of grammar rules (prefixed 
	by <literal>G_</literal> to avoid name clashes) and of tokens and
	an EOF symbol. Tokens are wrapped in the constructor
	<literal>HappyTok :: UserDefTok -> GSymbol</literal>. 
	</para>
	<para>
	The <literal>Branch</literal> type represents a match for some 
	right-hand side of a production, containing semantic information 
	(see below)
	and a list of sub-analyses. Each of these is a node in the graph.
	Note that tokens are represented as childless nodes that span 
	one input position. Empty productions will appear as childless nodes
	that start and end at the same position. 
	</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-using-compiling">
        <title>Compiling the parser</title>
        <para>
	<application>Happy</application> will generate two files, and these
	should be compiled as normal Haskell files. 
	If speed is an issue, then you should use the <option>-O</option>
	flags etc with the driver code, and if feasible, with the parser 
	tables too. 
        </para>
        <para>
        You can also use the <option>--ghc</option> flag to trigger certain
	<application>GHC</application>-specific optimizations. At present,
	this just causes use of unboxed types in the tables and in some key
	code. 
	Using this flag causes relevant <application>GHC</application>
	option pragmas to be inserted into the generated code, so you shouldn't
	have to use any strange flags (unless you want to...).
        </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="sec-glr-semantics">
      <title>Including semantic results</title>

      <para>
      This section discusses the options for including semantic information
      in grammars. 
      </para>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-semantics-intro">
        <title>Forms of semantics</title>
        <para>
	Semantic information may be attached to productions in the 
	conventional way, but when more than one analysis is possible, 
	the use of the semantic information must change. 
	Two schemes have been implemented, which we call 
	<emphasis>tree decoding</emphasis>
	and <emphasis>label decoding</emphasis>. 
	The former is for simple applications, where there is not much 
	ambiguity and hence where the effective unpacking of the parse
	forest isn't a factor. This mode is quite similar to the 
	standard mode in <application>Happy</application>.
	The latter is for serious applications, where sharing is important
	and where processing of the forest (eg filtering) is needed. 
	Here, the emphasis is about providing rich labels in nodes of the
	the parse forest, to support such processing. 
        </para>
	<para>
	The default mode is labelling. If you want the tree decode mode,
	use the <option>--decode</option> flag.
	</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-semantics-tree">
        <title>Tree decoding</title>
        <para>
	Tree decoding corresponds to unpacking the parse forest to individual
	trees and collecting the list of semantic results computed from 
	each of these. It is a mode intended for simple applications, 
	where there is limited ambiguity.
	You may access semantic results from components of a reduction 
	using the dollar variables. 
	As a working example, the following is taken from the 
	<literal>expr-tree</literal> grammar in the examples.
	Note that the type signature is required, else the types in use
	can't be determined by the parser generator.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
	E :: {Int}		-- type signature needed
	  : E '+' E  { $1 + $3 }
	  | E '*' E  { $1 * $3 }
	  | i        { $1 }
        </programlisting>
	<para>
	This mode works by converting each of the semantic rules into
	functions (abstracted over the dollar variables mentioned),
	and labelling each <literal>Branch</literal> created from a
	reduction of that rule with the function value.
	This amounts to <emphasis>delaying</emphasis> the action of the 
	rule, since we must wait until we know the results of all of 
	the sub-analyses before computing any of the results. (Certain
	cases of packing can add new analyses at a later stage.)
	</para>
	<para>
	At the end of parsing, the functions are applied across relevant 
	sub-analyses via a recursive descent. The main interface to this
	is via the class and entry function below. Typically, 
	<literal>decode</literal> should be called on the root of the 
	forest, also supplying a function which maps node names to their
	list of analyses (typically a partial application of lookup in
	the forest value).
	The result is a list of semantic values.
	Note that the context of the call to <literal>decode</literal>
	should (eventually) supply a concrete type to allow selection 
	of appropriate instance. Ie, you have to indicate in some way
	what type the semantic result should have.
	<literal>Decode_Result a</literal> is a synonym generated by
	<application>Happy</application>: for non-monadic semantics,
	it is equivalent to <literal>a</literal>; when monads are 
	in use, it becomes the declared monad type.
	See the full <literal>expr-eval</literal> example for more 
	information.
	</para>
        <programlisting>
	class TreeDecode a where
	       decode_b :: (ForestId -> [Branch]) -> Branch -> [Decode_Result a]
	decode :: TreeDecode a => (ForestId -> [Branch]) -> ForestId -> [Decode_Result a]
        </programlisting>

	<para>
	The GLR parser generator identifies the types involved in each
	semantic rule, hence the types of the functions, then creates 
	a union containing distinct types. Values of this union are 
	stored in the branches. (The union is actually a bit more complex:
	it must also distinguish patterns of dollar-variable usage, eg
	a function <literal>\x y -> x + y </literal> could be applied to 
	the first and second constituents, or to the first and third.)
	The parser generator also creates instances of the 
	<literal>TreeDecode</literal> class, which unpacks the semantic
	function and applies it across the decodings of the possible
	combinations of children. Effectively, it does a cartesian product
	operation across the lists of semantic results from each of the 
	children. Eg <literal>[1,2] "+" [3,4]</literal> produces
	<literal>[4,5,5,6]</literal>.
	Information is extracted from token values using the patterns 
	supplied by the user when declaring tokens and their Haskell
	representation, so the dollar-dollar convention works also.
	</para>
	<para>
	The decoding process could be made more efficient by using
	memoisation techniques, but this hasn't been implemented since
	we believe the other (label) decoding mode is more useful. (If someone
	sends in a patch, we may include it in a future release -- but this
	might be tricky, eg require higher-order polymorphism?
	Plus, are there other ways of using this form of semantic function?)
	</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-semantics-label">
        <title>Label decoding</title>
        <para>
	The labelling mode aims to label branches in the forest with 
	information that supports subsequent processing, for example
	the filtering and prioritisation of analyses prior to extraction
	of favoured solutions. As above, code fragments are given in
	braces and can contain dollar-variables. But these variables 
	are expanded to node names in the graph, with the intention of
	easing navigation.
	The following grammar is from the <literal>expr-tree</literal>
	example. 
        </para>
        <programlisting>
	E :: {Tree ForestId Int}
	  : E '+' E      { Plus  $1 $3 }
	  | E '*' E      { Times $1 $3 }
	  | i            { Const $1 }
        </programlisting>

        <para>
	Here, the semantic values provide more meaningful labels than 
	the plain structural information. In particular, only the 
	interesting parts of the branch are represented, and the 
	programmer can clearly select or label the useful constituents 
	if required. There is no need to remember that it is the first 
	and third child in the branch which we need to extract, because
	the label only contains those values (the `noise' has been dropped).
	Consider also the difference between concrete and abstract syntax.
	The labels are oriented towards abstract syntax.
	Tokens are handled slightly differently here: when they appear
	as children in a reduction, their informational content can 
	be extracted directly, hence the <literal>Const</literal> value
	above will be built with the <literal>Int</literal> value from 
	the token, not some <literal>ForestId</literal>.
        </para>

        <para>
	Note the useful technique of making the label types polymorphic 
	in the position used for forest indices. This allows replacement
	at a later stage with more appropriate values, eg. inserting
	lists of actual subtrees from the final decoding. 
        </para>
	<para>
	Use of these labels is supported by a type class
	<literal>LabelDecode</literal>, which unpacks values of the 
	automatically-generated union type <literal>GSem</literal>
	to the original type(s). The parser generator will create
	appropriate instances of this class, based on the type information
	in the grammar file. (Note that omitting type information leads
	to a default of <literal>()</literal>.)
	Observe that use of the labels is often like traversing an abstract
	syntax, and the structure of the abstract syntax type usually 
	constrains the types of constituents; so once the overall type
	is fixed (eg. with a type cast or signature) then there are no
	problems with resolution of class instances.
	</para>

        <programlisting>
	class LabelDecode a where
	       unpack :: GSem -> a
        </programlisting>

        <para>
	Internally, the semantic values are packed in a union type as
	before, but there is no direct abstraction step. Instead, the 
	<literal>ForestId</literal> values (from the dollar-variables)
	are bound when the corresponding branch is created from the 
	list of constituent nodes. At this stage, token information 
	is also extracted, using the patterns supplied by the user
	when declaring the tokens.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-semantics-tree-monad">
        <title>Monadic tree decoding</title>
        <para>
	You can use the <literal>%monad</literal> directive in the 
	tree-decode mode. 
	Essentially, the decoding process now creates a list of monadic 
	values, using the monad type declared in the directive. 
	The default handling of the semantic functions is to apply the
	relevant <literal>return</literal> function to the value being
	returned. You can over-ride this using the <literal>{% ... }</literal>
	convention. The declared <literal>(>>=)</literal> function is
	used to assemble the computations.
	</para>
	<para>
	Note that no attempt is made to share the results of monadic 
	computations from sub-trees. (You could possibly do this by 
	supplying a memoising lookup function for the decoding process.)
	Hence, the usual behaviour is that decoding produces whole 
	monadic computations, each part of which is computed afresh
	(in depth-first order) when the whole is computed.
	Hence you should take care to initialise any relevant state 
	before computing the results from multiple solutions. 
	</para>
	<para>
	This facility is experimental, and we welcome comments or 
	observations on the approach taken!
	An example is provided (<literal>examples/glr/expr-monad</literal>).
	It is the standard example of arithmetic expressions, except that
	the <literal>IO</literal> monad is used, and a user exception is
	thrown when the second argument to addition is an odd number.
	Running this example will show a zero (from the exception handler)
	instead of the expected number amongst the results from the other
	parses.
	</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-glr-misc">
      <title>Further information</title>

      <para>
      Other useful information...
      </para>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-misc-examples">
        <title>The GLR examples</title>
        <para>
	The directory <literal>examples/glr</literal> contains several examples 
	from the small to the large. Please consult these or use them as a 
	base for your experiments. 
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-misc-graphs">
        <title>Viewing forests as graphs</title>
        <para>
	If you run the examples with <application>GHC</application>, each
	run will produce a file <literal>out.daVinci</literal>. This is a
	graph in the format expected by the <emphasis>daVinci</emphasis> 
	graph visualization tool. 
	(See <ulink url="http://www.informatik.uni-bremen.de/~davinci/"/>
	for more information. Educational use licenses are currently
	available without charge.) 
        </para>
	<para>
	We highly recommend looking at graphs of parse results - it really 
	helps to understand the results. 
	The graphs files are created with Sven Panne's library for 
	communicating with <emphasis>daVinci</emphasis>, supplemented 
	with some extensions due to Callaghan. Copies of this code are 
	included in the examples directory, for convenience.
	If you are trying to view large and complex graphs, contact Paul
	Callaghan (there are tools and techniques to make the graphs more 
	manageable). 
	</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-misc-applications">
        <title>Some Applications of GLR parsing</title>
        <para>
	GLR parsing (and related techniques) aren't just for badly written
	grammars or for things like natural language (NL) where ambiguity is 
	inescapable. There are applications where ambiguity can represent
	possible alternatives in pattern-matching tasks, and the flexibility
	of these parsing techniques and the resulting graphs support deep
	analyses. Below, we briefly discuss some examples, a mixture from 
	our recent work and from the literature. 
        </para>

	<variablelist>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>Gene sequence analysis</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       Combinations of structures within gene sequences can be 
	       expressed as a grammar, for example a "start" combination
	       followed by a "promoter" combination then the gene proper. 
	       A recent undergraduate project has used this GLR implementation
	       to detect candiate matches in data, and then to filter these
	       matches with a mixture of local and global information. 
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>Rhythmic structure in poetry</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       Rhythmic patterns in (English) poetry obey certain rules, 
	       and in more modern poetry can break rules in particular ways
	       to achieve certain effects. The standard rhythmic patterns
	       (eg. iambic pentameter) can be encoded as a grammar, and 
	       deviations from the patterns also encoded as rules. 
	       The neutral reading can be parsed with this grammar, to 
	       give a forest of alternative matches. The forest can be 
	       analysed to give a preferred reading, and to highlight 
	       certain technical features of the poetry. 
	       An undergraduate project in Durham has used this implementation 
	       for this purpose, with promising results. 
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>Compilers -- instruction selection</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       Recent work has phrased the translation problem in 
	       compilers from intermediate representation to an 
	       instruction set for a given processor as a matching
	       problem. Different constructs at the intermediate 
	       level can map to several combinations of machine 
	       instructions. This knowledge can be expressed as a 
	       grammar, and instances of the problem solved by 
	       parsing. The parse forest represents competing solutions,
	       and allows selection of optimum solutions according
	       to various measures. 
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>Robust parsing of ill-formed input</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       The extra flexibility of GLR parsing can simplify parsing
	       of formal languages where a degree of `informality' is allowed.
	       For example, Html parsing. Modern browsers contain complex
	       parsers which are designed to try to extract useful information
	       from Html text which doesn't follow the rules precisely,
	       eg missing start tags or missing end tags.
	       Html with missing tags can be written as an ambiguous grammar,
	       and it should be a simple matter to extract a usable 
	       interpretation from a forest of parses. 
	       Notice the technique: we widen the scope of the grammar, 
	       parse with GLR, then extract a reasonable solution.
	       This is arguably simpler than pushing an LR(1) or LL(1)
	       parser past its limits, and also more maintainable.
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	     <term>Natural Language Processing</term>
	     <listitem>
	       <para>
	       Ambiguity is inescapable in the syntax of most human languages.
	       In realistic systems, parse forests are useful to encode
	       competing analyses in an efficient way, and they also provide
	       a framework for further analysis and disambiguation. Note 
	       that ambiguity can have many forms, from simple phrase 
	       attachment uncertainty to more subtle forms involving mixtures 
	       of word senses. If some degree of ungrammaticality is to be
	       tolerated in a system, which can be done by extending the 
	       grammar with productions incorporating common forms of 
	       infelicity, the degree of ambiguity increases further. For
	       systems used on arbitrary text, such as on newspapers, 
	       it is not uncommon that many sentences permit several 
	       hundred or more analyses. With such grammars, parse forest
	       techniques are essential. 
	       Many recent NLP systems use such techniques, including
	       the Durham's earlier LOLITA system - which was mostly 
	       written in Haskell.
	       </para>
	     </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-misc-workings">
        <title>Technical details</title>
        <para>
	The original implementation was developed by Ben Medlock, 
	as his undergraduate final year project, 
	using ideas from Peter Ljungloef's Licentiate thesis
	(see <ulink url="http://www.cs.chalmers.se/~peb/parsing"/>, and 
	we recommend the thesis for its clear analysis of parsing 
	algorithms). 
	Ljungloef's version produces lists of parse trees, but Medlock
	adapted this to produce an explicit graph containing parse structure
	information. He also incorporated
	the code into <application>Happy</application>.
        </para>

        <para>
	After Medlock's graduation, Callaghan extended the code to 
	incorporate semantic information, and made several improvements
	to the original code, such as improved local packing and 
	support for hidden left recursion. The performance of the
	code was significantly improved, after changes of representation
	(eg to a chart-style data structure)
	and technique. Medlock's code was also used in several student
	projects, including analysis of gene sequences (Fischer) and
	analysis of rhythmic patterns in poetry (Henderson).
        </para>

        <para>
	The current code implements the standard GLR algorithm extended 
	to handle hidden left recursion. Such recursion, as in the grammar
	below from Rekers [1992], causes the standard algorithm to loop 
	because the empty reduction <literal>A -> </literal> is always 
	possible and the LR parser will not change state. Alternatively,
	there is a problem because an unknown (at the start of parsing) 
	number of <literal>A</literal>
	items are required, to match the number of <literal>i</literal>
	tokens in the input.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
	S -> A Q i | + 
	A -> 
        </programlisting>
	<para>
	The solution to this is not surprising. Problematic recursions 
	are detected as zero-span reductions in a state which has a 
	<literal>goto</literal> table entry looping to itself. A special 
	symbol is pushed to the stack on the first such reduction, 
	and such reductions are done at most once for any token 
	alternative for any input position.
	When popping from the stack, if the last token being popped 
	is such a special symbol, then two stack tails are returned: one 
	corresponding to a conventional pop (which removes the
	symbol) and the other to a duplication of the special symbol
	(the stack is not changed, but a copy of the symbol is returned). 
	This allows sufficient copies of the empty symbol to appear
	on some stack, hence allowing the parse to complete.
	</para>

	<para>
	The forest is held in a chart-style data structure, and this supports
	local ambiguity packing (chart parsing is discussed in Ljungloef's 
	thesis, among other places). 
	A limited amount of packing of live stacks is also done, to avoid 
	some repetition of work. 
	</para>

        <para>
	[Rekers 1992] Parser Generation for Interactive Environments,
	PhD thesis, University of Amsterdam, 1992. 
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-misc-filter">
        <title>The <option>--filter</option> option</title>
        <para>
	You might have noticed this GLR-related option. It is an experimental
	feature intended to restrict the amount of structure retained in the 
	forest by discarding everything not required for the semantic
	results. It may or it may not work, and may be fixed in a future
	release.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-misc-limitations">
        <title>Limitations and future work</title>
	<para>
	The parser supports hidden left recursion, but makes no attempt
	to handle cyclic grammars that have rules which do not consume any 
	input. If you have a grammar like this, for example with rules like
	<literal>S -> S</literal> or 
	<literal>S -> A S | x; A -> empty</literal>, the implementation will 
	loop until you run out of stack - but if it will happen, it often 
	happens quite quickly! 
	</para>
        <para>
	The code has been used and tested frequently over the past few years, 
	including being used in several undergraduate projects. It should be
	fairly stable, but as usual, can't be guaranteed bug-free. One day
	I will write it in Epigram!
	</para>
        <para>
	If you have suggestions for improvements, or requests for features,
	please contact Paul
	Callaghan. There are some changes I am considering, and some 
	views and/or encouragement from users will be much appreciated. 
	Further information can be found on Callaghan's
	<ulink url="http://www.dur.ac.uk/p.c.callaghan/happy-glr">GLR parser
	page</ulink>.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-glr-misc-acknowledgements">
        <title>Thanks and acknowledgements</title>
        <para>
	Many thanks to the people who have used and tested this software
	in its various forms, including Julia Fischer, James Henderson, and
	Aarne Ranta.
        </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

<!-- Invoking ============================================================ -->

  <chapter id="sec-invoking">
    <title>Invoking <application>Happy</application></title>

    <para>An invocation of <application>Happy</application> has the following syntax:</para>

<screen>$ happy [ <emphasis>options</emphasis> ] <emphasis>filename</emphasis> [ <emphasis>options</emphasis> ]</screen>

    <para>All the command line options are optional (!) and may occur
    either before or after the input file name. Options that take
    arguments may be given multiple times, and the last occurrence
    will be the value used.</para>

    <para>There are two types of grammar files,
    <filename>file.y</filename> and <filename>file.ly</filename>, with
    the latter observing the reverse comment (or literate) convention
    (i.e. each code line must begin with the character
    <literal>&gt;</literal>, lines which don't begin with
    <literal>&gt;</literal> are treated as comments).  The examples
    distributed with <application>Happy</application> are all of the
    .ly form.</para>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>literate grammar files</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The flags accepted by <application>Happy</application> are as follows:</para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-o</option> <replaceable>file</replaceable></term>
	<term><option>--outfile</option>=<replaceable>file</replaceable></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Specifies the destination of the generated parser module.
	  If omitted, the parser will be placed in
          <replaceable>file</replaceable><literal>.hs</literal>,
	  where <replaceable>file</replaceable> is the name of the input
          file with any extension removed.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-i</option><optional><replaceable>file</replaceable></optional></term>
	<term><option>--info</option><optional>=<replaceable>file</replaceable></optional></term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>info file</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para> Directs <application>Happy</application> to produce an info file
          containing detailed information about the grammar, parser
          states, parser actions, and conflicts.  Info files are vital
          during the debugging of grammars.  The filename argument is
          optional (note that there's no space between
          <literal>-i</literal> and the filename in the short
          version), and if omitted the info file will be written to
          <replaceable>file</replaceable><literal>.info</literal> (where
          <replaceable>file</replaceable> is the input file name with any
          extension removed).</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-t</option> <replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	<term><option>--template</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term> 
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>template files</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>Instructs <application>Happy</application> to use this directory
          when looking for template files: these files contain the
          static code that <application>Happy</application> includes in every
          generated parser.  You shouldn't need to use this option if
          <application>Happy</application> is properly configured for your
          computer.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-m</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable></term>
	<term><option>--magic-name</option>=<replaceable>name</replaceable></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para> <application>Happy</application> prefixes all the symbols it uses internally
          with either <literal>happy</literal> or <literal>Happy</literal>.  To use a
          different string, for example if the use of <literal>happy</literal>
          is conflicting with one of your own functions, specify the
          prefix using the <option>-m</option> option.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-s</option></term>
	<term><option>--strict</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>NOTE: the <option>--strict</option> option is
	  experimental and may cause unpredictable results.</para>

	  <para>This option causes the right hand side of each
	  production (the semantic value) to be evaluated eagerly at
	  the moment the production is reduced.  If the lazy behaviour
	  is not required, then using this option will improve
	  performance and may reduce space leaks.  Note that the
	  parser as a whole is never lazy - the whole input will
	  always be consumed before any input is produced, regardless
	  of the setting of the <option>--strict</option> flag.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-g</option></term>
	<term><option>--ghc</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>GHC</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>back-ends</primary>
	    <secondary>GHC</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>Instructs <application>Happy</application> to generate a parser
	  that uses GHC-specific extensions to obtain faster code.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-c</option></term>
	<term><option>--coerce</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>coerce</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>back-ends</primary>
	    <secondary>coerce</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para> Use GHC's <literal>unsafeCoerce#</literal> extension to
          generate smaller faster parsers.  Type-safety isn't
          compromised.</para>

	  <para>This option may only be used in conjuction with
          <option>-g</option>.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-a</option></term>
	<term><option>--arrays</option></term> 
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>arrays</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>back-ends</primary>
	    <secondary>arrays</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para> Instructs <application>Happy</application> to generate a parser
          using an array-based shift reduce parser.  When used in
          conjunction with <option>-g</option>, the arrays will be
          encoded as strings, resulting in faster parsers.  Without
          <option>-g</option>, standard Haskell arrays will be
          used.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-d</option></term>
	<term><option>--debug</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>debug</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>back-ends</primary>
	    <secondary>debug</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>Generate a parser that will print debugging
	  information to <literal>stderr</literal> at run-time,
	  including all the shifts, reductions, state transitions and
	  token inputs performed by the parser.</para>

	  <para>This option can only be used in conjunction with
	  <option>-a</option>.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-?</option></term>
	<term><option>--help</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Print usage information on standard output then exit
	  successfully.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-V</option></term>
	<term><option>--version</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Print version information on standard output then exit
	  successfully. Note that for legacy reasons <option>-v</option>
	  is supported, too, but the use of it is deprecated.
	  <option>-v</option> will be used for verbose mode when it is
	  actually implemented.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
    </variablelist>

  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-grammar-files">
    <title>Syntax of Grammar Files</title>
    
    <para>The input to <application>Happy</application> is a text file containing
    the grammar of the language you want to parse, together with some
    annotations that help the parser generator make a legal Haskell
    module that can be included in your program.  This section gives
    the exact syntax of grammar files. </para>

    <para>The overall format of the grammar file is given below:</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;optional module header&gt;
&lt;directives&gt;
%%
&lt;grammar&gt;
&lt;optional module trailer&gt;
</programlisting>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>module</primary>
      <secondary>header</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>module</primary>
      <secondary>trailer</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>If the name of the grammar file ends in <literal>.ly</literal>, then
    it is assumed to be a literate script.  All lines except those
    beginning with a <literal>&gt;</literal> will be ignored, and the
    <literal>&gt;</literal> will be stripped from the beginning of all the code
    lines.  There must be a blank line between each code section
    (lines beginning with <literal>&gt;</literal>) and comment section.
    Grammars not using the literate notation must be in a file with
    the <literal>.y</literal> suffix.</para>
    
    <sect1 id="sec-lexical-rules">
      <title>Lexical Rules</title>

<para>Identifiers in <application>Happy</application> grammar files must take the following form (using
the BNF syntax from the Haskell Report):</para>

<programlisting>
        id      ::= alpha { idchar }
                  | ' { any{^'} | \' } '
                  | " { any{^"} | \" } "

        alpha   ::= A | B | ... | Z
                  | a | b | ... | z

        idchar  ::= alpha
                  | 0 | 1 | ... | 9
                  | _
</programlisting>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-module-header">
      <title>Module Header</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>module</primary>
	<secondary>header</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>This section is optional, but if included takes the
      following form:</para>

<programlisting>
{  
&lt;Haskell module header&gt;
}
</programlisting>

      <para>The Haskell module header contains the module name,
      exports, and imports.  No other code is allowed in the
      header---this is because <application>Happy</application> may need to include
      its own <literal>import</literal> statements directly after the user
      defined header.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-directives">
      <title>Directives</title>

      <para>This section contains a number of lines of the form:</para>

<programlisting>
%&lt;directive name&gt; &lt;argument&gt; ...
</programlisting>

      <para>The statements here are all annotations to help
      <application>Happy</application> generate the Haskell code for the grammar.
      Some of them are optional, and some of them are required.</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-token-type">
	<title>Token Type</title>

<programlisting>
%tokentype   { &lt;valid Haskell type&gt; }
</programlisting>

	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%tokentype</literal></primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>(mandatory) The <literal>%tokentype</literal> directive gives the
        type of the tokens passed from the lexical analyser to the
        parser (in order that <application>Happy</application> can supply types for
        functions and data in the generated parser).</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-tokens">
	<title>Tokens</title>

<programlisting>
%token &lt;name&gt; { &lt;Haskell pattern&gt; }
       &lt;name&gt; { &lt;Haskell pattern&gt; }
       ...
</programlisting>

	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%token</literal></primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>(mandatory) The <literal>%token</literal> directive is used to
        tell <application>Happy</application> about all the terminal symbols used
        in the grammar.  Each terminal has a name, by which it is
        referred to in the grammar itself, and a Haskell
        representation enclosed in braces.  Each of the patterns must
        be of the same type, given by the <literal>%tokentype</literal>
        directive.</para>

	<para>The name of each terminal follows the lexical rules for
        <application>Happy</application> identifiers given above.  There are no
        lexical differences between terminals and non-terminals in the
        grammar, so it is recommended that you stick to a convention;
        for example using upper case letters for terminals and lower
        case for non-terminals, or vice-versa.</para>

	<para><application>Happy</application> will give you a warning if you try
        to use the same identifier both as a non-terminal and a
        terminal, or introduce an identifier which is declared as
        neither.</para>

	<para>To save writing lots of projection functions that map
        tokens to their components, you can include
        <literal>&dollar;&dollar;</literal> in your Haskell pattern. For
        example:</para>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>&dollar;&dollar;</literal></primary>
	</indexterm>

<programlisting>
%token INT { TokenInt $$ }
       ...
</programlisting>

<para>This makes the semantic value of <literal>INT</literal> refer to the first argument
of <literal>TokenInt</literal> rather than the whole token, eliminating the need for
any projection function.</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-parser-name">
	<title>Parser Name</title>

<programlisting>
%name &lt;Haskell identifier&gt; [ &lt;non-terminal&gt; ]
...
</programlisting>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%name</literal></primary>
	</indexterm>

	<para>(optional) The <literal>%name</literal> directive is followed by
        a valid Haskell identifier, and gives the name of the
        top-level parsing function in the generated parser.  This is
        the only function that needs to be exported from a parser
        module.</para>

	<para>If the <literal>%name</literal> directive is omitted, it
        defaults to <literal>happyParse</literal>.</para>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><function>happyParse</function></primary>
	</indexterm>

	<para>The <literal>%name</literal> directive takes an optional
	second parameter which specifies the top-level non-terminal
	which is to be parsed.  If this parameter is omitted, it
	defaults to the first non-terminal defined in the
	grammar.</para>

	<para>Multiple <literal>%name</literal> directives may be
	given, specifying multiple parser entry points for this
	grammar (see <xref linkend="sec-multiple-parsers"/>).  When
	multiple <literal>%name</literal> directives are given, they
	must all specify explicit non-terminals.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-monad-decl">
	<title>Monad Directive</title>

<programlisting>
%monad { &lt;type&gt; } { &lt;then&gt; } { &lt;return&gt; }
</programlisting>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%monad</literal></primary>
	</indexterm>

	<para>(optional) The <literal>%monad</literal> directive takes three
        arguments: the type constructor of the monad, the
        <literal>then</literal> (or <literal>bind</literal>) operation, and the
        <literal>return</literal> (or <literal>unit</literal>) operation.  The type
        constructor can be any type with kind <literal>* -&gt; *</literal>.</para>

	<para>Monad declarations are described in more detail in <xref
        linkend="sec-monads"/>.</para>
	
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-lexer-decl">
	<title>Lexical Analyser</title>

<programlisting>
%lexer { &lt;lexer&gt; } { &lt;eof&gt; }
</programlisting>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%lexer</literal></primary>
	</indexterm>

	<para>(optional) The <literal>%lexer</literal> directive takes two
        arguments: <literal>&lt;lexer&gt;</literal> is the name of the lexical
        analyser function, and <literal>&lt;eof&gt;</literal> is a token that
        is to be treated as the end of file.</para>

	<para>Lexer declarations are described in more detail in <xref
        linkend="sec-lexers"/>.</para>
	
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-prec-decls">
	<title>Precedence declarations</title>

<programlisting>
%left     &lt;name&gt; ...
%right    &lt;name&gt; ...
%nonassoc &lt;name&gt; ...
</programlisting>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%left</literal> directive</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%right</literal> directive</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%nonassoc</literal> directive</primary>
	</indexterm>

	<para>These declarations are used to specify the precedences
	and associativity of tokens.  The precedence assigned by a
	<literal>%left</literal>, <literal>%right</literal> or
	<literal>%nonassoc</literal> declaration is defined to be
	higher than the precedence assigned by all declarations
	earlier in the file, and lower than the precedence assigned by
	all declarations later in the file.</para>

	<para>The associativity of a token relative to tokens in the
	same <literal>%left</literal>, <literal>%right</literal>, or
	<literal>%nonassoc</literal> declaration is to the left, to
	the right, or non-associative respectively.</para>

	<para>Precedence declarations are described in more detail in
	<xref linkend="sec-Precedences"/>.</para>
      </sect2>
      
      <sect2 id="sec-expect">
      	<title>Expect declarations</title>
<programlisting>
%expect &lt;number&gt;
</programlisting>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary><literal>%expect</literal> directive</primary>
	</indexterm>
	
	<para>(optional) More often than not the grammar you write
	will have conflicts. These conflicts generate warnings. But
	when you have checked the warnings and made sure that Happy
	handles them correctly these warnings are just annoying. The
	<literal>%expect</literal> directive gives a way of avoiding
	them. Declaring <literal>%expect
	<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> is a way of telling
	Happy &ldquo;There are exactly <replaceable>n</replaceable>
	shift/reduce conflicts and zero reduce/reduce conflicts in
	this grammar. I promise I have checked them and they are
	resolved correctly&rdquo;.  When processing the grammar, Happy
	will check the actual number of conflicts against the
	<literal>%expect</literal> declaration if any, and if there is
	a discrepancy then an error will be reported.</para>
	
	<para>Happy's <literal>%expect</literal> directive works
	exactly like that of yacc.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-grammar">
      <title>Grammar</title>

      <para>The grammar section comes after the directives, separated
      from them by a double-percent (<literal>%%</literal>) symbol.
      This section contains a number of
      <emphasis>productions</emphasis>, each of which defines a single
      non-terminal.  Each production has the following syntax:</para>
      <indexterm>
	<primary><literal>%%</literal></primary>
      </indexterm>

<programlisting>
&lt;non-terminal&gt; [ :: { &lt;type&gt; } ]
        :  &lt;id&gt; ... {[%] &lt;expression&gt; }
      [ |  &lt;id&gt; ... {[%] &lt;expression&gt; }
        ... ]
</programlisting>

      <para>The first line gives the non-terminal to be defined by the
      production and optionally its type (type signatures for
      productions are discussed in <xref
      linkend="sec-type-signatures"/>).</para>

      <para>Each production has at least one, and possibly many
      right-hand sides.  Each right-hand side consists of zero or more
      symbols (terminals or non-terminals) and a Haskell expression
      enclosed in braces.</para>

      <para>The expression represents the semantic value of the
      non-terminal, and may refer to the semantic values of the
      symbols in the right-hand side using the meta-variables
      <literal>&dollar;1 ... &dollar;n</literal>.  It is an error to
      refer to <literal>&dollar;i</literal> when <literal>i</literal>
      is larger than the number of symbols on the right hand side of
      the current rule. The symbol <literal>&dollar;</literal> may be
      inserted literally in the Haskell expression using the sequence
      <literal>\&dollar;</literal> (this isn't necessary inside a
      string or character literal).</para>

      <para>Additionally, the sequence <literal>&dollar;&gt;</literal>
      can be used to represent the value of the rightmost symbol.</para>

      <para>A semantic value of the form <literal>{% ... }</literal> is a
      <emphasis>monadic action</emphasis>, and is only valid when the grammar
      file contains a <literal>%monad</literal> directive (<xref
      linkend="sec-monad-decl"/>).  Monadic actions are discussed in
      <xref linkend="sec-monads"/>.</para>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>monadic</primary>
	<secondary>action</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Remember that all the expressions for a production must
      have the same type.</para>

      </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-module-trailer">
      <title>Module Trailer</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>module</primary>
	<secondary>trailer</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The module trailer is optional, comes right at the end of
      the grammar file, and takes the same form as the module
      header:</para>

<programlisting>
{
&lt;Haskell code&gt;
}
</programlisting>

      <para>This section is used for placing auxiliary definitions
      that need to be in the same module as the parser.  In small
      parsers, it often contains a hand-written lexical analyser too.
      There is no restriction on what can be placed in the module
      trailer, and any code in there is copied verbatim into the
      generated parser file.</para>

      </sect1>
    </chapter>
  
  <chapter id="sec-info-files">
    <title>Info Files</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>info files</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>(section under construction)</para>

  </chapter>
  
  <chapter id="sec-tips">
    <title>Tips</title>

    <para>This section contains a lot of accumulated lore about using
    <application>Happy</application>.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-performance-tips">
      <title>Performance Tips</title>

      <para>How to make your parser go faster:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist>

	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>GHC</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para> If you are using GHC, generate parsers using the
          <literal>-a -g -c</literal> options, and compile them using GHC with
          the <literal>-fglasgow-exts</literal> option.  This is worth a
          <emphasis>lot</emphasis>, in terms of compile-time,
          execution speed and binary size <footnote><para>omitting the
          <literal>-a</literal> may generate slightly faster parsers,
          but they will be much bigger.</para></footnote>.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> The lexical analyser is usually the most performance
          critical part of a parser, so it's worth spending some time
          optimising this.  Profiling tools are essential here.  In
          really dire circumstances, resort to some of the hacks that
          are used in the Glasgow Haskell Compiler's interface-file
          lexer.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Simplify the grammar as much as possible, as this
          reduces the number of states and reduction rules that need
          to be applied.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>recursion, left vs. right</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para> Use left recursion rather than right recursion
          wherever possible.  While not strictly a performance issue,
          this affects the size of the parser stack, which is kept on
          the heap and thus needs to be garbage collected.</para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>


    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="sec-compilation-time">
      <title>Compilation-Time Tips</title>

      <para>We have found that compiling parsers generated by
      <application>Happy</application> can take a large amount of time/memory, so
      here's some tips on making things more sensible:</para>

      <itemizedlist>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Include as little code as possible in the module
          trailer.  This code is included verbatim in the generated
          parser, so if any of it can go in a separate module, do
          so.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>type</primary>
	    <secondary>signatures in grammar</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para> Give type signatures for everything (see <xref
          linkend="sec-type-signatures"/>.  This is reported to improve
          things by about 50%.  If there is a type signature for every
          single non-terminal in the grammar, then <application>Happy</application>
          automatically generates type signatures for most functions
          in the parser.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Simplify the grammar as much as possible (applies to
          everything, this one).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Use a recent version of GHC.  Versions from 4.04
	  onwards have lower memory requirements for compiling
	  <application>Happy</application>-generated parsers.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para> Using <application>Happy</application>'s <literal>-g -a -c</literal>
	  options when generating parsers to be compiled with GHC will
	  help considerably.</para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="sec-finding-errors">
      <title>Finding Type Errors</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>type</primary>
	<secondary>errors, finding</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Finding type errors in grammar files is inherently
      difficult because the code for reductions is moved around before
      being placed in the parser.  We currently have no way of passing
      the original filename and line numbers to the Haskell compiler,
      so there is no alternative but to look at the parser and match
      the code to the grammar file.  An info file (generated by the
      <literal>-i</literal> option) can be helpful here.</para>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>type</primary>
	<secondary>signatures in grammar</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Type signature sometimes help by pinning down the
      particular error to the place where the mistake is made, not
      half way down the file.  For each production in the grammar,
      there's a bit of code in the generated file that looks like
      this:</para>

<programlisting>
HappyAbsSyn&lt;n&gt; ( E )
</programlisting>
      <indexterm>
	<primary><literal>HappyAbsSyn</literal></primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>where <literal>E</literal> is the Haskell expression from the
      grammar file (with <literal>&dollar;n</literal> replaced by
      <literal>happy_var_n</literal>).  If there is a type signature for this
      production, then <application>Happy</application> will have taken it into
      account when declaring the HappyAbsSyn datatype, and errors in
      <literal>E</literal> will be caught right here.  Of course, the error may
      be really caused by incorrect use of one of the
      <literal>happy_var_n</literal> variables.</para>

      <para>(this section will contain more info as we gain experience
      with creating grammar files.  Please send us any helpful tips
      you find.)</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-conflict-tips">
      <title>Conflict Tips</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>conflicts</primary>
      </indexterm>
      
      <para>Conflicts arise from ambiguities in the grammar.  That is,
      some input sequences may possess more than one parse.
      Shift/reduce conflicts are benign in the sense that they are
      easily resolved (<application>Happy</application> automatically selects the
      shift action, as this is usually the intended one).
      Reduce/reduce conflicts are more serious.  A reduce/reduce
      conflict implies that a certain sequence of tokens on the input
      can represent more than one non-terminal, and the parser is
      uncertain as to which reduction rule to use.  It will select the
      reduction rule uppermost in the grammar file, so if you really
      must have a reduce/reduce conflict you can select which rule
      will be used by putting it first in your grammar file.</para>

      <para>It is usually possible to remove conflicts from the
      grammar, but sometimes this is at the expense of clarity and
      simplicity.  Here is a cut-down example from the grammar of
      Haskell (1.2):</para>

<programlisting>
exp     : exp op exp0
        | exp0

exp0    : if exp then exp else exp
        ...
        | atom

atom    : var
        | integer
        | '(' exp ')'
        ...
</programlisting>

      <para>This grammar has a shift/reduce conflict, due to the
      following ambiguity.  In an input such as</para>

<programlisting>
if 1 then 2 else 3 + 4
</programlisting>

      <para>the grammar doesn't specify whether the parse should be</para>

<programlisting>
if 1 then 2 else (3 + 4)
</programlisting>

      <para>or</para>

<programlisting>
(if 1 then 2 else 3) + 4
</programlisting>

      <para>and the ambiguity shows up as a shift/reduce conflict on
      reading the 'op' symbol.  In this case, the first parse is the
      intended one (the 'longest parse' rule), which corresponds to
      the shift action.  Removing this conflict relies on noticing
      that the expression on the left-hand side of an infix operator
      can't be an <literal>exp0</literal> (the grammar previously said
      otherwise, but since the conflict was resolved as shift, this
      parse was not allowed).  We can reformulate the
      <literal>exp</literal> rule as:</para>

<programlisting>
exp     : atom op exp
        | exp0
</programlisting>

      <para>and this removes the conflict, but at the expense of some
      stack space while parsing (we turned a left-recursion into a
      right-recursion).  There are alternatives using left-recursion,
      but they all involve adding extra states to the parser, so most
      programmers will prefer to keep the conflict in favour of a
      clearer and more efficient parser.</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-lalr">
	<title>LALR(1) parsers</title>

	<para>There are three basic ways to build a shift-reduce
        parser.  Full LR(1) (the `L' is the direction in which the
        input is scanned, the `R' is the way in which the parse is
        built, and the `1' is the number of tokens of lookahead)
        generates a parser with many states, and is therefore large
        and slow.  SLR(1) (simple LR(1)) is a cut-down version of
        LR(1) which generates parsers with roughly one-tenth as many
        states, but lacks the power to parse many grammars (it finds
        conflicts in grammars which have none under LR(1)). </para>

	<para>LALR(1) (look-ahead LR(1)), the method used by
        <application>Happy</application> and
        <application>yacc</application>, is tradeoff between the two.
        An LALR(1) parser has the same number of states as an SLR(1)
        parser, but it uses a more complex method to calculate the
        lookahead tokens that are valid at each point, and resolves
        many of the conflicts that SLR(1) finds.  However, there may
        still be conflicts in an LALR(1) parser that wouldn't be there
        with full LR(1).</para>

      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-happy-ghci">
      <title>Using Happy with <application>GHCi</application></title>
      <indexterm><primary><application>GHCi</application></primary>
      </indexterm>
      
      <para><application>GHCi</application>'s compilation manager
      doesn't understand Happy grammars, but with some creative use of
      macros and makefiles we can give the impression that
      <application>GHCi</application> is invoking Happy
      automatically:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Create a simple makefile, called
	  <filename>Makefile_happysrcs</filename>:</para>

<programlisting>HAPPY = happy
HAPPY_OPTS = 

all: MyParser.y

%.hs: %.y
	$(HAPPY) $(HAPPY_OPTS) $&lt; -o $@</programlisting>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Create a macro in GHCi to replace the
          <literal>:reload</literal> command, like so (type this all
          on one line):</para>

<screen>:def rh (\_ -> System.system "make -f Makefile_happysrcs"
   >>= \rr -> case rr of { System.ExitSuccess -> return ":reload" ; 
                           _ -> return "" })</screen>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Use <literal>:myreload</literal>
	  (<literal>:my</literal> will do) instead of
	  <literal>:reload</literal> (<literal>:r</literal>).</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <index/>
</book>
